Guide to the Lee Baxandall Papers TAM.151
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Lee Baxandall Papers
1888-2001
1965-1989
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Baxandall, Lee
TAM.151
36.5 Linear Feet in 25 manuscript boxes, 23 record cartons, 3 media boxes, 1 oversize box, and 1 shared box
The Lee Baxandall Papers (dates 1888-2001, bulk 1965-1989) contain writings, research files, and correspondence related to the works of publisher and writer Lee Baxandall. Lee Baxandall was a literary critic, poet, and playwright who specialized in Marxism and aesthetics. Baxandall studied English and Comparative Literature at the University of Wisconsin—Madison where he became attracted to New Left scholarship, and later became an editor for the journal Studies on the Left from 1960-1967. His papers contain research files he compiled in the 1960s and 1970s on Marxist and leftist writers, artists, and intellectuals from the mid-19th to the early-20th century. The collection also contains manuscripts and correspondence related to Polish philosopher Stefan Morawski, who was a frequent collaborator of Baxandall's. Materials from a 2004 accretion largely relate to Baxandall's work after 1975 and contain an assortment of research files, as well as drafts, photographs, pamphlets, scripts and periodicals related to Baxandall's poetry, plays, and advocacy of naturism.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Materials were donated by Lee Baxandall in 1975 and 2004. One folder of correspondence between Lee Baxandall and publishers, which was found in the repository, was added to the collection in 2014. One folder of materials related to the small press Green Mountain Editions was found in repository and added to the collection in 2016. The accession numbers associated with these gifts are 1998.012, 2004.037, 2014.083, and 2016.068.
In 2025, materials from accession 2019.056, which is associated with Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Printed Ephemera Collection on Subjects (PE 029), were transferred to this collection.
Arrangement
The Lee Baxandall Papers are divided into three series.
Series I: Research Files contain of two sets of research files that are arranged in alphabetical order by name or topic.
Series II: Translations and Lee Baxandall Publications are contained in rough groupings by publication title or record type.
Materials in Series III: 2004 Accretion are the least well arranged and are contained in rough groupings based on record type and topic. In many cases these grouping are broken-up across several boxes and contain materials related to files in Series I and Series II.
Historical Note
Lee Baxandall was a publisher and literary critic who specialized in Marxism and aesthetics. Born in Oshkosh, Wisconsin in 1935, he received an MA in English from the University of Wisconsin--Madison where he also pursued doctoral studies in comparative literature and wrote extensively on Marxist theatre, art, and literature. At the University of Wisconsin he became attracted to New Left scholarship, and later became an editor for the journal Studies on the Left from 1960-1967. Baxandall had a special interest in the works of German playwright and poet Bertolt Brecht and translated many of his plays into English. He edited several anthologies on Marxism and literature, and published essays on art criticism in periodicals including: The Nation, Partisan Review, Journal of Aesthetics and Art Criticism, and the New York Times.
Throughout his publishing career, Baxandall worked closely with Polish philosopher Stefan Morawski. He translated several of Morawski's works on aesthetics into English for publication in the United States. In 1973 Baxandall and Morawski co-edited the anthology Karl Marx and Friedrich Engels on Art and Literature, which they later republished in 1974 for the series Documents on Marxist Aesthetics (DOMA). Baxandall and Morawski worked together for several years to produce an additional 11 volumes in the series, but it appears that they were never completed.
Baxandall lived in New York City throughout much of the 1960s, but returned to his home in Oshkosh following the death of his father in 1970. Baxandall ran the publishing company Green Mountain Editions, which produced issues of the periodical Green Mountain Quarterly between 1975 and 1977. Baxandall was also a proponent of naturism and the Free Beach movement. He was the founder of the Naturist Society in Oshkosh, Wisconsin, and wrote a popular guide to nude beaches in 1986. He died in Oshkosh in 2008.
Scope and Content Note
The Lee Baxandall Papers (dates 1888-2001, bulk 1965-1989) contain writings, research files, and correspondence related to the works of leftist literary critic Lee Baxandall. Research files in this collection focus predominantly on Marxist scholars and intellectuals, with the most intensive research on the works of Brecht. These files were compiled in the 1960s and 1970s and largely consist of Baxandall's notes and copies of theoretical works by a variety of mid-19th and early-20th century artists and intellectuals. A small portion of these files more specifically address topics related to early-American socialist theater.
The collection also contains drafts of Baxandall's writings and translations of works by Marxist intellectuals. The majority of his translations relate to the writings of Polish philosopher Stefan Morawski, and include extensive correspondence between the two. Materials related to Baxandall's writings also include translation of the works of Wilhelm Reich, and correspondence with publishers and colleagues regarding his various projects.
A second donation of Baxandall's papers received in 2004 includes additional research files, drafts, notes, correspondence, and newspaper clippings related to Baxandall's work in literary criticism. A substantial amount of these materials consist of additional correspondence and drafts related to Baxandall's work with Stefan Morawski. These materials are largely dated after 1975, and reflect both the personal and professional relationship between Baxandall and Morawski. There are also drafts of Baxandall's plays and poetry, which include copies of scripts, photographs, flyers, and published works. Baxandall's best represented plays are Potsy and Claws of the Eagle, Claws of the Jaguar. Additionally, the collection contains periodicals, essays, and ephemera related to Baxandall's interest in the politics of sexual expression and his advocacy of naturism. It also includes correspondence and publications produced by the small press Green Mountain Editions in Oshkosh, Wisconsin.
Communist aesthetics.; Socialism and the arts -- Europe.; Socialism and the arts -- United States.; Socialism and theater.; Theater -- Political aspects.; Nudism.; Brecht, Bertolt, 1898-1956; Morawski, Stefan; Baxandall, Lee
- Series I: Research Files, 1888-1976; 10.5 Linear Feet in 24 boxes
  Scope and Content Note
  This series consists of two sets of Lee Baxandall's research files. The first set of files make up the bulk of the series and focus on the works of Marxist scholars and artists. The files were compiled in the 1960s and 1970s and include Baxandall's typed and handwritten notes, scholarly articles, correspondence related to research inquiries, short draft segments, and copies of plays and essays by 19th and 20th century intellectuals. These files also contain a small amount material produced in the 1930s and 1940s including pamphlets, newspaper clippings, and collected correspondence related to Baxandall's research subjects. The largest portion of these files relate to Baxandall's research on playwright Bertolt Brecht.
  The second set of research files relate more specifically to early-American socialist theater, art, and literature. These files largely consist of Baxandall's handwritten and typed notes on individuals and venues that championed Socialist theater in the early-20th century. Among these materials are several files on the works of painter Robert Koehler, with a particular focus on his oil painting "The Strike." These materials include correspondence with museums and owners of the artist's paintings, and relate to Baxandall's efforts to purchase and publicize Koehler's works. They also include an original 1888 letter to Koehler from painter James McNeil Whistler.
  Notecards in this series contain abstracts on topics and individuals featured in Baxandall's research.
  - Aaron, Daniel - Behan, Dominic, 1948-1976 (Box 1)
  - Bentley, Eric - Brecht Society, 1962-1975 (Box 2)
  - Brecht, 1959-1964 (Box 3)
  - Brecht, 1949-1976 (Box 4)
  - Brecht, 1959-1973 (Box 5)
  - Brecht: The Mother - China, 1946-1974 (Box 6)
  - China - Cuba: Cultural Congress, 1960-1971 (Box 7)
  - Cuban Arts: Variety - Douglas, Emory, 1947-1976 (Box 8)
  - Dreiser, Theodore - Folsom, Michael B., 1946-1975 (Box 9)
  - Folsom, Michael B. - Gorelik, M., 1946-1973 (Box 10)
  - Gorky, Maxim - Hughes, Langston, 1935-1975 (Box 11)
  - Humboldt, Charles - Laxness, Hallador, 1945-1974 (Box 12)
  - League of American Writers - Margolies, David, 1933-1974 (Box 13)
  - Margiategui, J.C - New Art Examiner (Chicago), 1933-1976 (Box 14)
  - New German Critique - Portuondo, Jose Antonio, 1948-1976 (Box 15)
  - Potamkin, Harry Alan - Samson, Leon, 1949-1975 (Box 16)
  - San Juan, Epifanio - Stone, Joan, 1964-1978 (Box 17)
  - Stevenson, Philip - Vietnam, 1957-1975 (Box 18)
  - Vygotskii, L.S. - Zipes, Jack, 1936-1974 (Box 19)
  - Koehler "The Strike", 1888-1971 (Box 19, Box 20)
  - Early-American Socialist Art and Theater, 1970-1973 (Box 21, Box 20)
  - Art and Socialism: Notecards, undated (Box 29)
  - Art and Socialism: Notecards, undated (Box 30)
  - Art and Socialism: Notecards, undated (Box 31)
- Series II: Translations and Lee Baxandall Publications, 1962-1976; 3.5 Linear Feet in 6 boxes
  This series contains drafts and correspondence regarding Baxandall's translations of Marxist scholarship and his work in Marxism literary criticism. The bulk of the translations in this series contain works on Marxist aesthetics by Stefan Morawski. Materials related to Baxandall's collaborations with Morawski also include extensive correspondence with the Polish philosopher. Additionally the series contains translations and research on the works of Wilhelm Reich and some additional correspondence related to Baxandall's writings and publishing career. This correspondence is mixed with an assortment of clippings and ephemera more generally related to radical theater from the 1970s.
  - Stefan Morawski: Marx and Engels, 1968-1970 (Box 22)
  - Stefan Morawski: "What is a Work of Art?", 1971-1972 (Box 22)
  - Stefan Morawski: "Artistic Value", 1966-1971 (Box 22, Box 23)
  - Stefan Morawski: "The Criteria of Aesthetic Evaluation", 1968-1972 (Box 23)
  - Stefan Morawski: "Expression", 1972-1974 (Box 23)
  - Stefan Morawski: Mimesis/Realism, 1969-1970 (Box 24, Box 23)
  - Stefan Morawski: L'Absolu et la Forme, circa 1970s (Box 24)
  - Stefan Morawski: "Inquiries into the Fundamentals of Aesthetics", circa 1974 (Box 25, Box 24)
  - Stefan Morawski: "I Presupposti Filosofica di Karl Liebknecht", 1973 (Box 25)
  - Stefan Morawski letters to Lee Baxandall, 1962-1973 (Box 25, Box 26)
  - Wilhelm Reich: Sex-Pol, 1970-1974 (Box 26)
  - Correspondence Regarding Baxandall Publications, 1975-1976 (Box 27)
  - Stefan Morawski: Inquiries into the Fundamentals of Aesthetics, 1972-1973
  - Clippings and Ephemera: Art and Radicalism, 1970-1975 (Box 27)
- Series III: 2004 Accretion, 1950-2001; 22.5 Linear Feet in 22 boxes and 1 shared box
  This series contains the remainder of Lee Baxandall's papers, which were donated to Tamiment Library in 2004. These materials contain an assortment of research files, drafts, notes, correspondence, and newspaper clippings related to Baxandall's writings. Writings in this series relate to Baxandall's work in literary criticism and include drafts of articles, essays, lectures. The series contains additional materials related to his collaborations with Stefan Morawski. The bulk of these materials relate to the anthology Marx and Engels on Art and Literature, which they co-edited together. These materials consist of drafts and correspondence regarding the licensing and the publication of a follow-up edition for the Documents in Marxist Aesthetics (DOMA) series. Drafts and research for subsequent volumes in the DOMA series are also included among these materials, but it appears that the later volumes were never completed.
  The series includes drafts of Baxandall's plays and theatrical sketches from the 1960s and 1970s. These materials contain a number of short sketches, drafts, production materials, and documents related to stage royalties of his plays. Materials related to these plays include flyers, scripts, correspondence, and photographs of stage productions. The plays that are most well represented are Potsy and the Claws of the Eagle, Claws of the Jaguar.
  Clippings and ephemera in this series consist of an assortment of newspaper articles, playbills, pamphlets, and flyers on radicalism in theater and the arts. Scattered throughout these materials is a small amount of Baxandall's correspondence, most of which is related to art criticism and written from his office at Green Mountain Editions, where he worked as a publisher in the 1970s. This series also contains several folders of personal correspondence between 1963 and 1978.
  The series contains several partial alphabetical runs of research and writing files. These grouping may be incomplete, and may not correlate to other alphabetical runs elsewhere in the series.
  - Correspondence and Drafts: Works with Stefan Morawski, 1962-1999 (Box 32)
  - Clippings and Ephemera: Art and Radicalism, 1975-1984 (Box 33)
  - Writing Files: A-M, 1975-1981 (Box 34)
  - Writing Files: R-W, 1972-1985 (Box 35)
  - Drafts and Manuscripts: "Documents on Marxist Aesthetics" (DOMA) and Radical Perspectives in the Arts, 1972-1985 (Box 35)
  - Writing Files: W-Z, 1961-1989 (Box 36)
  - Periodicals: Green Mountain Quarterly, Studies on the Left, and journals on European Art and Literature, 1960-1989 (Box 36)
  - Periodicals: Drama and the Arts, 1960-1991 (Box 37)
  - Research Files: Sexuality and Sexual Expression, and American Family Association Journal, 1980-1997 (Box 38)
  - Writing Files: Louis Fraina, Max Eastman, Dramataury, B-C, 1960s-1970s (Box 39)
  - Drafts for Publication: Marxist Literature, 1960s-1970s (Box 39)
  - Notes and Clippings: Writers and Artists, 1952-1980 (Box 40)
  - Writing Files: Marxism and Aesthetics, Georgi Plekhanov, and Edward Albee, 1986-1989 (Box 41)
  - Writing and Research Files: Baxandall Plays, 1961-1974 (Box 42)
  - Personal Correspondence, 1961-1978 (Box 43, Box 42)
  - Drafts and Outlines: Marxists on Art and Literature, 1971-1977 (Box 43)
  - Plays: Claws of the Eagle, Claws of the Jaguar and Potsy, 1966-2001 (Box 44)
  - Writing Files: Original Poetry and Art Criticism, M-Z, 1962-1977 (Box 45)
  - Index Cards: English Literature, R-Z, undated (Box 45)
  - Writing and Research Files: Louis Fraina, Oscar Lovell Triggs, Literature and Imperialism, 1965-1983 (Box 46)
  - Index Cards: English Literature, A-Q, undated (Box 46)
  - Writing Files: Art and Literary Criticism, A-L, 1960s-1980s (Box 47)
  - Correspondence and Drafts: Morawski Translations and Publisher Correspondence, 1970-2000 (Box 48)
  - Research and Writings on Bertolt Brecht, 1975-1995 (Box 49)
  - Publication Correspondence and Outlines: "Documents on Marxist Aesthetics" (DOMA), 1962-1973 (Box 49)
  - Research and Writing Files: DOMA II and Henriette Roland-Holst, 1969-1980 (Box 50)
  - Politics and Sexual Expression: Wilhelm Reich and Sex-Pol, 1969-1980 (Box 50)
  - Politics and Sexual Expression: Wilhelm Reich, Free Family Movement and, Aktionsanalytische Organisation (AAO) Friedrichshof Commune, 1975-1991 (Box 51)
  - Clippings and Ephemera: Theater, 1965-1985 (Box 52)
  - Periodicals: Wet Magazine, 1978-1983 (Box 28)
  - Comments on "Chapters in American Literary Criticism" by Joseph Freedman, 1976 (Box Shared Tamiment 193, Folder 3)